Charles Henry Brent Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Charles Henry Brent Papers 1860-1991 (bulk 1901-1929)
MSS23564
Brent, Charles Henry, 1862-1929
14,740 items
72 containers
32 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Clergyman and missionary. Correspondence, diaries, sermon notes, speeches and articles, reports, memoranda, family and personal correspondence, obituaries, Bibles, printed matter, memorabilia, scrapbooks, and photographs documenting Brent's career as a clergyman and missionary.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Abbott, Lyman, 1835-1922--Correspondence.; Brent family.; Brent, Charles Henry, 1862-1929.; Brent, Helen C. C.; Bryce, James Bryce, Viscount, 1838-1922--Correspondence.; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947--Correspondence.; Chamberlain, Austen, Sir, 1863-1937--Correspondence.; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933--Correspondence.; Davidson, Randall Thomas, 1848-1930--Correspondence.; Drury, Samuel S. (Samuel Smith), 1878-1938--Correspondence.; Forbes, W. Cameron (William Cameron), 1870-1959--Correspondence.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964--Correspondence.; Knox, Philander C. (Philander Chase), 1853-1921--Correspondence.; Lang, Cosmo Gordon, 1864-1945--Correspondence.; Morgan, J. Pierpont (John Pierpont), 1837-1913--Correspondence.; Mott, John R. (John Raleigh), 1865-1955--Correspondence.; Northcliffe, Alfred Harmsworth, Viscount, 1865-1922--Correspondence.; Ogilby, Remsen B., -1943.; Page, Walter Hines, 1855-1918--Correspondence.; Peabody, Francis Greenwood, 1847-1936--Correspondence.; Pepper, George Wharton, 1867-1961--Correspondence.; Pershing, John J. (John Joseph), 1860-1948--Correspondence.; Reid, Whitelaw, 1837-1912--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919--Correspondence.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937--Correspondence.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930--Correspondence.; Willcox, Reginald N.--Correspondence.; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927--Correspondence.
Organizations
Episcopal Church--Missions--Philippines.; Episcopal Church. Diocese of Western New York.; United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces--Chaplains.; World Conference on Faith and Order.
Subjects
Ecumenical movement.; Military chaplains.; Narcotics--Congresses.; Opium.; World War, 1914-1918--Religious aspects.
Occupations
Clergy.; Missionaries.
Provenance
The papers of Charles Henry Brent, clergyman and missionary, were deposited in the Library of Congress in 1954 by Helen C. C. Brent who converted the deposit to a gift in 1955. Further gifts were received from Frederick W. Kates in 1957 and 1958. Two other groups of papers were received and organized later. An addition of 1979 was given in installments between 1971 and 1979 by Whitney Hale, Frederick W. Kates, Roger W. Drury, and W. Scott Brent. An addition of 1996 was given in installments between 1989 and 1992 by Elizabeth Willcox Thomson, Douglas B. Thomson, and Philippiniana Sacra, Fathers' Residence, University of Santo Tomas, Manila, Philippines.
Additional Guides
The papers are the subject of a press release issued by the Library of Congress on 7 March 1955. Published notes appeared in the Library's Information Bulletin, vol. 14 (28 Feb. 1955), pp. 1-2, and vol. 16 (16 Aug. 1957), pp. 410-411. In addition, the material was described in the Library of Congress Quarterly Journal of Current Acquisitions, vol. 12 (May 1955), p. 122, and vol. 15 (May 1958), pp. 190-191.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Charles Henry Brent are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1862, Apr. 9 Born, Newcastle, Ontario, Canada
1884 A.B. with honors in classics, Trinity College, University of Toronto, Canada
1885 1987 Undermaster, Trinity College School, Port Hope, Canada
1886 Ordained deacon, Protestant Episcopal Church
1887 Ordained priest
1889 A.M., Trinity College, University of Toronto, Canada
1891 Became an American citizen
1891 1901 Assistant rector, St. Stephen's Church, Boston, Mass.
1899 Published With God in the World. New York: Longmans, Green
1901 1918 Missionary bishop to the Philippine Islands
1903 1914 Member of committee appointed by the Philippine government for investigation of the opium question
1904 Paddock lecturer, General Theological Seminary, New York, N.Y.
1907 William Belden Noble lecturer, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1908 1919 Chief commissioner for the United States and president of the first International Opium Commission, Shanghai, China
1910 Attended International Missionary Conference, Edinburgh, Scotland
1911 1912 Chairman, U.S. delegation to the International Opium Conference, Hague, Netherlands (president of the conference, 1912)
1916 Published A Master Builder, Being the Life and Letters of Henry Yates Satterlee, First Bishop of Washington. New York: Longmans, Green
1918 Published The Mount of Vision, Being a Study of Life in Terms of the Whole. New York: Longmans, Green Elected Bishop, Diocese of Western New York, Protestant Episcopal Church
1918 1919 Chief, Chaplain Service, American Expeditionary Forces, France
1919 1929 Bishop, Diocese of Western New York, Protestant Episcopal Church
1920 Chairman, Geneva meeting to plan the World Conference on Faith and Order
1921 Duff lecturer, Edinburgh, Glasgow, and Aberdeen universities, Scotland.
1923 Appointed by President Warren G. Harding to the Advisory Committee on Narcotics of the League of Nations
1924 Last attendance at opium conference
1926 1928 Bishop in charge of American Episcopal churches in Europe
1927 President, first World Conference on Faith and Order
1928 Represented the Protestant Episcopal Church of America at the installation of Cosmo Gordon Lang as Archbishop of Canterbury; last public appearance
1929, Mar. 27 Died, Lausanne, Switzerland
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Charles Henry Brent span the years 1860-1991, but are concentrated in the period 1901-1929. The papers document Brent's service as first missionary bishop to the Philippine Islands representing the Protestant Episcopal Church in America, 1901-1918; his term as chief of the Chaplain Service of the American Expeditionary Forces, 1918-1919; his activities as a bishop of the church and as a member of various conferences on the opium problem; and his presidency of the World Conference on Faith and Order, 1927. The papers consist of correspondence, chiefly 1908-1929, sermon notes, diaries, manuscripts of books and articles, speeches, a subject file on the opium conferences, scrapbooks, and printed material. There is also a related group of papers assembled by Remsen B. Ogilby, who died in 1943 before he had completed his planned biography of Bishop Brent. Additions contain family and personal correspondence, obituaries, articles, speeches, photographs and miscellaneous material concerning his church missions, conference work, and personal relationships.
Prominent correspondents include Lyman Abbott, James Bryce, Nicholas Murray Butler, Austen Chamberlain, Calvin Coolidge, Randall Davidson, W. Cameron Forbes, Herbert Hoover, Philander Chase Knox, Cosmo Gordon Lang, Jr., Pierpont Morgan, John R. Mott, Alfred C. W. H. Northcliffe, Walter Hines Page, Francis G. Peabody, George Wharton Pepper, John J. Pershing, Whitelaw Reid, Theodore Roosevelt, Elihu Root, William Howard Taft, and Leonard Wood.
The 1979 Addition spans the years 1888-1976, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1888-1929. Brent corresponded fairly regularly with his sisters, and letters to them as well as those to his mother comment on subjects such as his missionary work in the Philippines, attendance at various religious and political international conferences, and the Protestant Episcopal diocese of Western New York.
The diary in this addition, dated 1907, relates to diaries in the original collection. The general correspondence is strictly of a personal nature. One folder, consisting of letters to Samuel W. Drury and his family, is composed entirely of copies of originals not included in this collection. The Writings include notes of sermons given in 1902 and several poems and talks. The Miscellany is comprised of biographical data presented at an American bicentennial ceremony honoring Brent in 1976.
Correspondents among this additional material include Brent's sisters Evelyn, Edith S, and Helen C. C. Brent, and his mother Frances Sophia Cummings Brent. Other individuals to whom he wrote were Mrs. John Markoe and Edith Eaton (Mrs. William B. Cutter).
The 1996 Addition spans the years 1919-1991, but is concentrated in the period 1919-1929. It consists of correspondence, articles and addresses by Brent, obituaries, memorials, photographs, and miscellaneous material. The correspondence dates from 1919-1929 and contains letters written almost exclusively to Reginald N. Willcox and family, rector of Saint Luke's Church, Jamestown, N. Y., a parish in Brent's diocese of Western New York. The issues mentioned chiefly concern parish financial problems and Willcox's family. Speeches and writings are predominantly addresses before the conventions of the diocese of Western New York, 1922-1925, and the articles by Brent concern religious matters.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in eleven series:
Diaries, 1901-1929
General Correspondence and Other Papers, 1886-1949
Sermon Notes and Related Material, 1890-1929
Book, Article, and Speech File, 1908-1928
Material Relating to Brent's Death, 1929-1930
Miscellany
Subject File: Conferences on Opium, 1860-1931
Scrapbooks, 1896-1928
Printed Matter
Biographer's Papers, circa 1890-1943
Additions, 1888-1991
Container List
- Diaries, 1901-1929 (Box 1-3)
  Bound diaries.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1901-1906 (Box 1)
  - 1909-1917 (Box 2)
  - 1918-1919 (Box 3)
  - 1921
  - 1923-1926
  - 1929
- General Correspondence and Other Papers, 1886-1949 (Box 4-20)
  Letters sent and received.
  Arranged chronologically by month.
  - 1886-1900 (Box 4)
  - 1901 (Box 5)
  - 1902-1907 (Box 6)
  - 1908, Jan.-Aug. (Box 7)
  - 1908, Sept.-1909-Dec. (Box 8)
  - 1910-1911 (Box 9)
  - 1912-1914 (Box 10)
  - 1915, Jan.-Sept. (Box 11)
  - 1915, Oct.-1916, Oct (Box 12)
  - 1916, Nov.-1917, May (Box 13)
  - 1917, June-1918, Feb. (Box 14)
  - 1918, Mar.-Sept. (Box 15)
  - 1918, Oct.-1925, Dec. (Box 16)
  - 1926-1928 (Box 17)
  - 1929, undated (Box 18)
  - Brent, Helen C. C., correspondence, 1931-1949, undated
  - Gardiner, Robert H., correspondence, 1908-1924 (Box 19)
  - Brown, Ralph W., correspondence, 1924-1929 (Box 20)
- Sermon Notes and Related Material, 1890-1929 (Box 21-32)
  Bound and loose notes and related material.
  Arranged chronologically by year.
  - Bound (Box 21)
    - 1890-1897, (6 vols.)
    - 1893-1898, (7 vols.) (Box 22)
    - 1896-1898, (7 vols.) (Box 23)
    - 1897-1901, (10 vols.) (Box 24)
    - 1901-1909, (17 vols.) (Box 25)
    - 1910-1917, (14 vols.) (Box 26)
    - 1918-1928, undated, (14 vols.) (Box 27)
    - Undated, (15 vols.) (Box 28)
  - Unbound (Box 29)
    - 1917-1922
    - 1923-1927, undated (Box 30)
    - Undated (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 1897-1929, undated, (15 vols.) (Box 32)
- Book, Article, and Speech File, 1908-1928 (Box 33-34)
  Holograph and typewritten drafts and galley proofs.
  Arranged by type of material and alphabetically by title.
  - Books (Box 33)
    - "Adventures in Prayer"
    - "The Commonwealth"
    - "The Mystic Sense"
    - Untitled, chapter III ("Our Opportunities")
  - Articles and speeches (Box 34)
    - Articles
      - "European Nations and Christian Statesmanship"
      - "On `Peril' Among Robbers"
    - Speeches
      - Edinburgh, Scotland, lectures, 1921
      - Various, 1908-1928, undated
- Material Relating to Brent's Death, 1929-1930 (Box 35-36)
  Letters received chronologically arranged by month. Also material concerning the Bishop Brent Memorial Fund.
  - Letters received, 1929 (Box 35)
  - Bishop Brent Memorial Fund, 1929-1930 (Box 36)
- Miscellany (Box 37)
  Memorabilia, commissions, licenses, passports, poems, fragments, financial papers, photographs, and Bibles.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Bibles (Box 37)
  - Memorabilia
  - Commissions, licenses, passports, and fragments
  - Photographs
  - Financial papers
- Subject File: Conferences on Opium, 1860-1931 (Box 38-41)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, and printed and near-printed matter relating to Brent's service on various conferences on opium.
  Arranged largely by conference.
  - Conferences on opium (Box 38)
    - 1909-1912
    - 1923, May-June (Box 39)
    - 1924, Nov.-1925, Jan. (Box 40)
    - 1909-1925 (Box 41)
  - Personal conference file, 1923-1929
  - Printed matter, 1860-1931
  - State Department, correspondence, 1923
  - Miscellany, 1921-1924
- Scrapbooks, 1896-1928 (Box 42-43)
  Clippings and typed copies of Brent's articles and editorials mounted in scrapbooks.
  Chronologically arranged.
  - 1896-1901, (2 vols.) (Box 42)
  - 1901-1928, (3 vols.) (Box 43)
- Printed Matter (Box 44-48)
  Pamphlets, clippings, and near-printed and miscellaneous material.
  Arranged by subject.
  - By and about Brent (Box 44)
  - Clippings (Box 45)
  - Geneva Convention, Geneva, Switzerland (Box 46)
  - Lanman-Orient
  - New York Diocese publications
  - Peace movement
  - Philippine Islands (Box 47)
  - St. Stephen's Church, Boston, Mass.
  - "Why the Church?"
  - World Conference on Faith and Order
  - Miscellany (Box 48)
- Biographer's Papers, circa 1890-1943 (Box 49-67)
  Correspondence, notes, and manuscripts assembled by Remsen B. Ogilby, including typed copies of Brent's letters and transcripts of excerpts from Brent's diaries, 1901-1929, and drafts of Ogilby's biography.
  A collection of holograph Brent letters is chronologically arranged by month. Most of the Ogilby correspondence has been reassembled into an alphabetical arrangement.
  - Holograph letters by Brent (Box 49)
    - 1890-1903
    - 1904-1910 (Box 50)
    - 1911-1915 (Box 51)
    - 1916-1929, undated (Box 52)
  - Transcript of excerpts from Brent's diaries (Box 53)
    - Vol. 1, 1901-1910
    - Vol. 2, 1911-1929 (Box 54)
  - Draft of "The Impatient Crusader" (Box 55)
  - Correspondence (Box 56)
    - A-B
    - C-G (Box 57)
    - H-L (Box 58)
    - Ma-Mi (Box 59)
    - Mo-Pepper (Box 60)
    - Pepper, George W. (Box 61)
    - Ph-R (Box 62)
    - S-V (Box 63)
    - W-Z and unarranged (Box 64)
  - Miscellaneous material (Box 65-67)
- Additions, 1888-1991 (Box 68-72)
  - 1979 Addition, 1888-1976 (Box 68-71)
    A diary, family and general correspondence, speeches and writings, and miscellany.
    Organized by type of material and further arranged alphabetically or chronologically where possible.
    - Diary, 1907 (Box 68)
    - Family correspondence, 1889-1929, undated
      - Brent, Frances Sophia Cummings (mother), 1897-1900
      - Brent, Edith S. (sister)
        - 1901-1917, (3 folders)
        - 1918-1929, undated, (2 folders) (Box 69)
      - Brent, Evelyn (sister), 1889-1929, undated, (3 folders)
      - Brent, Helen (sister)
        - 1910-1911
        - 1912-1929, undated, (3 folders) (Box 70)
      - "Dear Sisters" letters
        - 1911-1928, (3 folders)
        - 1929, undated, and fragments, (2 folders) (Box 71)
    - General correspondence, 1888-1929, undated
      - Drury, Samuel W. and family, 1905-1921
      - Eaton, Edith (Mrs. William B. Cutter), 1888-1893
      - Markoe, Mrs. John, 1910-1921, undated
      - Miscellaneous, 1918-1929
    - Miscellany, American Bicentennial memorial service honoring Brent, 1976
    - Speeches and writings, 1902-1928, undated
      - "A National Memorial to Our Soldier Dead," 1928
      - Notes
      - Poems and other writings, undated
  - 1996 Addition, 1919-1991 (Box 72)
    Correspondence, speeches and writings, biographical material, photographs, and printed items.
    Organized by type of material and chronologically therein where possible.
    - Correspondence, Reginald N. Willcox and family, 1919-1929, (2 folders) (Box 72)
    - Miscellany
      - Obituaries, memorials, and articles concerning Brent, 1929-1991, undated
      - Photographs, undated
      - Printed and near-printed items, 1919-1988, undated
    - Speeches and writings, 1922-1926, undated